Pound mss. IV, ca. 1915-1970 LMC 1870
Lilly Library
Pound mss. IV
ca. 1915-1970
Lilly Library
Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972.
LMC 1870
60 Items
The Pound mss. IV consist of articles, poems, plays, and other writings by various authors that were sent to Ezra or Dorothy Pound by those authors.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Ezra Pound was an expatriate American poet and critic and one of the leaders of the early modernist movement. Born in Idaho, he attended the University of Pennsylvania and went on to teach briefly at Wabash College in Crawfordsville, Indiana before traveling overseas and living in London, Paris, and Italy, then returning to the States in 1945. Pound went back to Italy in 1958 and died in Venice in 1972.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by author.
Scope and Content Note
Included is a carbon typescript of Noel Stock's The Life of Ezra Pound ( London: Routledge & Kegan Paul, 1970) with annotations and corrections by Dorothy Pound. Other authors represented include Louis Dudek, Robert Duncan, Achilles Fang, Giovanni Giovannini, Raymond Hughes, Hugh Kenner, D.D. Paige, Desmond Stewart, Henry Swabey, Peter Whigham, Robert McNair Wilson, and Stanislaus Yankowski.
Note on Indexing Term - "Literature--translating": Includes translations of works in various languages.
Related Material
See Pound mss. I, Pound mss. II, Pound mss. III, Pound mss. V, Pound mss. VI, Pound mss. VII,, also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Acquisition Information
Gift. Omar S. Pound, Princeton, New Jersey. 1986
Literature--translating; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972; Pound, Dorothy.; Stock, Noel. Life of Ezra Pound.; Dudek, Louis, 1918-2001.; Duncan, Robert, 1919-1988.; Fang, Achilles.; Giovannini, Giovanni.; Hughes, Raymond.; Kenner, Hugh.; Paige, D. D.; Stewart, Desmond, 1924-1981.; Swabey, Henry.; Whigham, Peter.; Wilson, R. McNair (Robert McNair), 1882-1963.; Yankowski, Stanislaus.
- Bunting, Basil. Poem: "The Spoils." T.(carbon)D.S. 10p. Moderate corrections in ink by author. 1951. Published in Poetry in 1951 and later published separately ()., 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Chang, Carsun. "Chu Chih-Yu, the 17th-Century Chinese Refugee philosopher in Japan and his Japanese disciples." T.D. 22p., with a few ink corrections. (Folder 2)
- Chilanti, Felice. "Going South--Desperation and Bandits." T.D. 3p. (possibly incomplete). Extensively corrected in EP's and DP's hands. Undated. (Folder 3)
- Cicogna, Giorgio. Poem: "Hymn to Mathematics." T.Ds. 5p. each of the original Italian text and of the English translation by Helen Rossetti Angeli.., ca. 1952 (Folder 4)
- Dolmetsch, Arnold. "17th and 18th Century Music." Galleys of pages 416-470, clean. 13 sheets., July 1915 (Folder 5)
- Dudek, Louis. Poems: "A Solitary Guest," "Les Innocents," "Wife," "Provençal Poets," and "The God Pan Hears Jazz." Ribbon/carbon mix of typescripts. 5p., four of the poems signed.., 1949 (Folder 6)
- Poems: "Moving Picture," "Romantic Matter," and "Calypso." T.Ds.S. 3p. each (Folder 6)
- Duncan, Robert. Poem: "A Description of Venice." T.(carbon). 23p., clean. (Folder 7)
- Untitled poem beginning "Great Venus came into the room." T.D. 1p., clean. (Folder 7)
- T.L.S. from Duncan to EP. 1p., but 1950s, describing his studies of oriental languages, etc., Undated (Folder 7)
- Duncan, Robert, et al. "A Canto for E.P." T.(carbon) 7p. but probably mid 1940s. Few minor pencilled changes and markings., Undated (Folder 8)
- Another copy, T.(carbon) 6p., with a few minor corrections, and pencilled notes by EP on verso of last page "copied. Washington.D.C.,"., December 27, 1946 (Folder 8)
- English, Maurice. Translation into English of poems by Eugenio Montale and Umberto Saba. Three printed broadsheets (approx. 16x12). Folded. (Folder 9)
- Ewart, Gavin and Jack Clark. "Uncle Tom's Cabin (Fragment of a Parody)" T.D. 2p. Published Poetry London., 1950 (Folder 10)
- Fang, Achilles. "Imagism and The Chinese Renaissance." T.(carbon)D. 26p., with some corrections by author and with Chinese ideograms inked in.., July 1952 (Folder 11)
- Fang, Achilles. "Some reflexions [sic] on the difficulty of translation." T.(ditto copy)D. 54p., with some corrections by author.. [Fang was a Sinologist at Harvard who was important to EP's Chinese studies]., 1952 (Folder 12)
- Gallup, Donald. "T.S. Elliot and Ezra Pound, Collaborators in Letters." T(photocopy)D. 35p., with some ink markings.., 1970 (Folder 13)
- Giovannini, Giovanni. "The Case of Ezra Pound." T.(carbon)D. 11p., with several corrections. With cover T.L.S.., 10 Dec. 1954 (Folder 14)
- Hart, Bill. "Nonsuch Land of Water." First chapter of book by William Beebe. T.D. 9p., with several corrections. Copied by Hart and sent to EP with a cover T.L.., 16 May 1956 (Folder 15)
- Howe, Henrietta. "The New Atlas." T.(carbon)D. 41p., with corrections.., No date, but 1950s (Folder 16)
- Hughes, Raymond. Play: "The King's Pleasure." T.(carbon)D. 89p., with some underlining.. [Hughes, a Welsh writer, was connected with the periodical "Four Pages."], Undated, but 1950s (Folder 17)
- Kenner, Hugh. "The Chisel," review of Basil Bunting's Poems: 1950. T.(carbon). 5p., with "Sent to Poetry - H.K." on top page, and envelope addressed to EP ()., 1951 (Folder 18)
- Kimball, Dudley. "Discussion Report: I" Printed galley. 1p., inscribed by author, Sept. 24, 1950 (Folder 19)
- Koch, Paul (under pseudonym Pablo Owens). Poems. T.Ds. ca. 50p., with some minor marks in EP's hand.ca.., 1951 (Folder 20)
- Mullins, Eustace. His Spirit Tower. Printed page proofs. ca. 50p. Published by Cleaner's Press in an edition of 99 copies., 1951 (Folder 21)
- Musgrave, Thea. "Five Songs." Holograph musical manuscript in ink, setting EP and Louis MacNiece poems to music. 18p. Probably unpublished. (Folder 22)
- Paige, D.D. "The Resurgence of Adib Jabbor." T.D. 11p., with a few corrections.., Undated (Folder 23)
- Pease, Maj. Frank. Play "'It's Gotta Get Worse!' A Slight Play for Joiners." T.(carbon)D. 17p., clean.., ca. 1952 (Folder 24)
- Pelo Pardi, Guilio del. "For World Peace." Translated from the Italian. T.(carbon) of Preface. 6p., clean.., 1924 (Folder 25)
- For World Peace. T.D., 9p. Accompanied by envelope from Giovanni Giovannini addressed to Dorothy Pound and postmarked., Dec. 10, 1954 (Folder 25)
- Pound, Ezra. Articles: "Poisoned Supply Pipes," T.(carbon)D. 4p., clean. (Folder 26)
- A Means of Communication, T.(carbon)D. 6p., clean. Translations from the Italian (translator unknown) from Orientamenti (Gallup A55). (Folder 26)
- Pound, Ezra. Essay: "Totalitarian Scholarship and the New Paideuma," edited by Douglas Fox (Gallup C1405). A.D. 9p., probably in hand of Douglas Fox. Published in Germany and You., 25 April 1937 (Folder 27)
- Quinn, Sister Bernetta. "Conclusion." Apparently the last chapter of her book Metamorphosis in Modern American Poetry. T.D. 15p., with a few corrections. (Folder 28)
- Rachewiltz, Boris de. Incantesimi e Scongiuri (Verona, Scheiwiller). Printed page proofs. 44p., with some corrections., 1958 (Folder 29)
- Somers, Homer L. Article: "Ezra Pound J'ayme; donc, Je suis." T.D. 5p. Probably a draft, with moderate corrections. [Somers was an American army officer who first met EP during his detention at Pisa in 1945.] (Folder 30)
- Stewart, Desmond. "The Memoirs of Alcibiades." T.(carbon)D. 138p., clean.., Undated (Folder 31)
- Stock, Noel. The Life of Ezra Pound. Carbon T.D. ca.600+ pages, with Noel Stock's corrections and queries to DP in blue; and with Dorothy Pound's corrections and replies to Stock in red., 1970 (Box 2, Folder s 1-5)
- Swabey, Henry. To the Editor, Calvacade. "The Confiscation Racket." T.(carbon)D.S. 2p., with "Draft for EP" in pencil. (Folder 6)
- Swabey, Henry. "Mental Blackout." T.D. 2p., plus 2 carbon copies. (Folder 7)
- Swabey, Henry (under pseudonym Enery der Swabe). "Middle Class Marathon." T.(carbon)D.S. 2p., with a few ink corrections.., Undated (Folder 8)
- Thomas, Jessie. "I Walked in My Garden" [music]. A.D.S., in pencil. 4p.. Inscribed to Mr. & Mrs. Pound,., 1948; May 5, 1951 (Folder 9)
- Villari, Luigi. "The Communist Defeat in Italy." T.(carbon)D. 2p., clean, with a short typed note appended by EP., June 14, 1948 (Folder 10)
- Whigham, Peter. "Conker Avenue and Other Poems." T.D. 36 p., with several corrections by author. Inscribed to DP (Folder 11)
- Whigham, Peter. "Ezra Pound." T.(mimeographed)D., 10p., with some corrections in ink.., ca. early 1950s (Folder 12)
- Wilson, R. McNair. Play: "Dukes Must Do It." T.(carbon)D. 133p., with some autograph corrections in ink.., Undated (Folder s 13-15)
- Yankowski, Stanislaus. "Ezra Pound's Translation of Sophocles." Published in EP's Women of Trachis(Gallup A72). T.(carbon)D. 9p., with a few corrections; accompanied by "Note on the CHOROI in the EP's Women of Trachis." T.D. 1p. Also, a probable later version, T.D., 8p. and a cover T.L.: SY to EP., 12 July 1954 (Folder 16)
- Unknown (but possibly by Villari or written for Il Tempo). "Colloquio con Il Camerata." T.(carbon)D. 4p., clean.., Undated (Folder 17)
- Unknown. Poem: "Dinner at the Acropolis (for Barbara). T.D. 1p.., Undated (Folder 18)
- Unknown. Article: "E Nato l'Uomo Cinque." T.(copy)D. 7p. In Italian.., Undated (Folder 19)
- Unknown. Untitled essay beginning "Elliot is beyond doubt...." T.(carbon)D. 2p., clean.., Undated (Folder 20)
- Unknown (but possibly by Eustace Mullins). Chapters 13-19 of a work on history of money, etc. T.D. 67p. (hand numbered pages 186-253). Chap. 13, titled: "Money in Europe in the 1930s."., Undated (Folder 21)
- Unknown. "The Nature of Our Quarrel with the Soviet Union." T.(carbon)D. 3p. (Folder 22)
- Unknown. Poems: "October," "Oh Lord Establish Thou the Labor of My Hands," and "My Shadow. T.Ds. 4p., clean. with EP's note: "Whose?" on last page. (Folder 23)
- Unknown. Poems. T.(carbons)D. 4p. 3/20/49, 3/21/49 and 3/27/49. Three pages are heavily corrected/revised, in pencil, by EP. (Folder 24)
- Unknown. Poems: "Spiritual Pilgrimage (Divina Comedia)," with " S.O.S." appended. T.(carbons). 2p., 1952/53 (Folder 25)
- Unknown. Essay: "Temper of the Whelk." T.D. 4p. Also a cover illustration in ink.., Undated (Folder 26)
- Yockey, Francis Parker. "Press release: What is behind the hanging of the eleven Jews in Prague?" Printed (mimeograph?). 9p. With a cover printed letter from Le Blanc Publishers. "For release Dec. 20th." [1953?] (Folder 27)